# XINLEI ZHANG

### RESEARCH INTERESTS & GOAL

My research interests lie in the **theories** and **applications** in **robotics**, including **state estimation** & **system dynamics**, **nonlinear control**, and **data-driven methods**. My goal is to advance robotics research by integrating artificial intelligence and control theory methods.

#### **EDUCATION**

## **1** South China University of Technology | Intelligent Manufacturing

09/2020 - 06/2024 (Expected)

Shien-Ming Wu School of Intelligent Engineering

**♀** Guangzhou, China

Overall GPA

3.75/4.0

**Related Courses** 

- Applied Calculus II 96/100, Linear Algebra 97/100, Probability and Statistics 89/100
- Artificial Intelligence Technology and Applications 90/100, Data Structure 91/100
- Sensor Technology and Applications 90/100, Mechatronics 92/100
- System Dynamics 91/100, Classical Control Theory 92/100

## PUBLICATION & PATENT

## On Ambiguity in 6-DoF Magnetic Pose Estimation 6 | First Author

11/2023

Xinlei Zhang, Shuda Dong and Heng Wang

Submitted to International Journal of Robotics Research, under the first-round review

A Virtual Ultrasonography Simulator for Skill Training Using Magnetic-Inertial Probe Tracking 03/2023 Heng Wang, Shuangyi Wang, Suqi Liu, Shuda Dong, Xinlei Zhang

CN Patent Pending, No.CN116312122A 🔗

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

The Lab of Magnetic-Controlled Robot, SCUT

09/2021-Present

Research Assistant, advised by Dr. Heng Wang 🐠

## 6-DoF Magnetic-Inertial Pose Estimation | Team Member

09/2021-12/2021

#### Contribution:

- \* Debugged the magnetic-inertial sensor and sensor-arduino-Matlab communication.
- \* Reviewed the literature regarding the magnetic-inertial pose estimation methods.
- \* Learned and completed the probabilistic modeling of magnetic-inertial sensor measuring process.
- \* Implemented the constrained extended Kalman filter (CEKF) to fuse a constant velocity model and magnetic-inertial sensor measurements to achieve pose estimation.
- \* Defined the ambiguity issue in magnetic-inertial pose estimation system and proposed its identification method, to analyze and interpret the observability in this nonlinear system.

#### · Outcome:

- \* Achieved millimeter-degree 6-DoF pose estimation accuracy in experiments.
- \* Applied for one CN patent.

#### On Ambiguity in 6-DoF Magnetic Pose Estimation | Research Leader

01/2022-Present

#### · Contribution:

- \* Utilized the geometry of the special Euclidean group to decouple position and orientation in ambiguity issue.
- \* Employed the numerical optimization method to tackle the non-linearity in magnetic field distribution.
- \* Systematized the framework to analyze the ambiguity issue in magnetic pose estimation systems, including its definition, categorization, identification algorithms and impact on pose estimation.
- \* Proposed the optimal magnetic source design in magnetic pose estimation system to achieve 6-DoF pose estimation without ambiguity.

- \* Derived the equation describing the dynamical nature of ambiguity issue.
- \* Designed and conducted experiments to verify the framework and the performance of the optimal system.

#### • Outcome:

- \* Achieved millimeter-degree-accuracy and unambiguous 6-DoF pose estimation with the prototype.
- \* Submitted one manuscript to **International Journal of Robotics Research**, under the first-round review.
- \* Earned recognition and funding through the Chinese National Training Program of Innovation and Entrepreneurship for Undergraduates, with a total funding amount of \$1300.

## RELATED COURSE PROJECTS

## Tendon-Driven and Flex Sensor Based Gesture Sensing Hand Exoskeleton **6** Team Leader Spring 2023

- 10 motors are controlled to stretch tendons attached to the hand exoskeleton, achieving independent control of all five fingers. Moreover, flex sensors are fixed with fingers to measure their bending extent, providing gesture information, to construct the closed-loop gesture control of fingers.
- **Key words:** PID Motor Control, 3D Modeling and Manufacturing of Exoskeleton, Tendon-driven Mechanism, Bending Sensor, Closed-loop Gesture Tracking.

## Wireless-Powered Animation System Displayed by Rotating LEDs & Team Leader

Fall 2022

- Multiple embedded system modules, motor-driving, infrared-monitoring, wireless-charging and sounding-effect, were controlled to present the self-designed animation based on the principle of persistence of vision.
- **Key words:** Wireless-charging Coil & Circuit Design, Infrared Sensor, Sounding Module, Animation Presented by Rotating LED Stripe.

## Omni-Motion, Bluetooth-control and Self-Reloading Automatic Catapult 6 | Team Leader | Spring 2022

- The **kinematic model** of the 4 omni-wheel motion was analyzed to achieve the **omni-direction control**. Remote operation was achieved using the **Bluetooth** device and **one self-designed android app**. Moreover, a self-reloading mechatronics device was developed by **3D printing**, **laser cutting and circuit design** technologies.
- **Key words:** Omni-motion UGV Design and Manufacturing, Bluetooth Module & Android App, Self-reloading Mechanism, Lever-Spring-Motor Shooting Mechanism.

## Machine Learning & IMU Based Classifier on Ping-Pong Players' Motion 🔗 | Team Leader Fall 2021

- Neural network and decision tree classifiers were ensembled to distinguish the motion of forehand drive and backhand stroke of a Ping-Pong player based on the inertial data. Moreover, One-class SVM and Local outlier factor were employed to detect wrong motions during training which may bring damage to the player's wrist.
- **Key words:** Inertial Sensor, Classifier: Neural Network & Decision Tree, Fault Detection: One-class SVM & Local Outlier Factor, Ping-Pong Training Monitoring.

## SELECTED AWARDS & HONORS &

## Mathematical Contest in Modeling

05/2023

Honorable Mention (Second-Class Award), Top 30%

## Alibaba Cloud Programming Contest in SCUT

03/2023

Third-Class Award, Top 15%

#### Undergraduate Internship Scholarship, China Scholarship Council & University of Alberta

08/2022

Only 1 in South China University of Technology and total 9 in China

National Contest on Micro Sensing and Intelligent Technology

10/2021

National First Prize & Excellent Defense, Top 4%

#### South China University of Technology Student Scholarship

Freshman Year

Third-Class University Scholarship, 7/55

#### OTHER-RESEARCH-ACTIVITIES

### Journalist Volunteer for School Invited Academic Speeches

03/2023-Present

I write 5-minute reading summary news of academic speeches for School Social Media Public Account

#### Student Memberships of many famous academic research communities

05/2022-Present

Student memberships of IEEE CSS, RAS, and virtual academic seminars hosted by CMU and UoT

### **SKILLS**

Languages: Chinese (Native), English (Fluent)

**Programming**: MATLAB & Simulink, Python, C, C++, R

Others: SolidWorks, CAD, Embedded System Development, Photo & Video Editing, LaTeX & Markdown